Guide to the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection ARC.212
Brooklyn Historical Society
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection
1819-1980
1847-1887
Brooklyn Historical Society
Beecher, Henry Ward
King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins)
Ellinwood, T. J. (Truman Jeremiah)
Plymouth Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.212
48.5 Cubic Feet in 75 boxes: 32 manuscript boxes, 38 flat boxes, and 6 small boxes
The Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection traces the career of the Reverend Henry Ward Beecher, the well known 19th century preacher, and the history of Plymouth Congregational Church, of which Beecher was the first pastor. Plymouth Church was a major institution in 19th century Brooklyn, first gaining recognition on national and international levels as Beecher's pulpit. Beecher was well known for his oratorical ability and for his vocal opposition to slavery and support of the Northern cause during the Civil War. He also spoke out on subjects ranging from women's suffrage and evolution to organized labor and temperance. Beecher was a popular figure despite controversy that surrounded his activities, including a charge of adultery that resulted in a widely reported trial in 1875. The collection relates principally to Beecher's pastorate at Plymouth Church from 1847 until his death in 1887. Other materials, ranging through 1980, concern the church's other pastors and the history of Plymouth Church itself, which consolidated with the Church of the Pilgrims in 1934. The papers provide insight into the church congregation's various activities, illustrate the history of Beecher's influence on his congregation and on 19th century congregationalism, and shed light on both the public and private life of a major American personality of the 19th century.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection was donated to the Center for Brooklyn History (formerly the Brooklyn Historical Society and Long Island Historical Society) by the church on October 29, 1983. The collection was created by Plymouth Church/Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims to document the history of the two churches as well as Plymouth Church's first pastor, Henry Ward Beecher.
The collection is artificial in that many items, especially those related to Beecher, appear to have been collected and donated over an extended period of time, often by congregants who happened upon materials loosely associated to the famous preacher and his time. The collection includes, for example, souvenirs from the Harriet Beecher Stowe House and memorials of the assassinated President Lincoln. Explicit documentation of the provenance of such items is lacking. One 1873 organ concert program was the gift of Frank J. Wilder.
Correspondence regarding the collection during the time it was held at Plymouth Church, written sometime after 1920, outlined a prospective plan for the collection. William Davenport, attorney and member of Plymouth Church, stated in the plan that "countless invaluable records especially of the Bethel S[abbath] S[chool] and Main S[abbath] S[chool] were lost [in the 1920 fire] besides scores of fine photographs, documents and other articles relating to the church's history." Davenport urged the active collection of papers and letters relating to prominent church figures, most notably Henry Ward Beecher, to be "secured,...preserved, and [transcribed]." His successful solicitation is evidenced in the numerous typed transcripts of original documents now found within the collection. In addition he called for the creation of "a card catalog of the books, pamphlets, manuscripts, and so forth." This suggestion was also heeded, and the resulting catalog is now housed by Center for Brooklyn History.
Arrangement
The Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection is organized in three series:
Series 1: Henry Ward Beecher, 1819-1958
Series 2: Plymouth Church, 1824-1980
Series 3: Images, circa 1840s-circa 1966
The first two series are further arranged into several sections that are described below at the series level. The series contain overlapping dates and materials. For example, those materials recording the daily workings of Plymouth Church during Henry Ward Beecher's tenure, such as Sunday School records, are found within Series 2: Plymouth Church, as their primary function illustrates the activities of the church, not Beecher. Similarly, the records of Beecher's Silver Wedding Anniversary, which, although organized by the church, relate directly to Beecher, are found in Series 1: Henry Ward Beecher.
Date ranges used on folders and for the collection as a whole were determined on a best effort basis within the time constraints of processing. Consequently there may be documents in folders with dates that fall outside the noted date range. This is particularly true for the many scrapbooks, newsclippings, and undated documents in the collection. An effort was made within processing constraints to place a circa date on these.
Biographical / Historical
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims Chronology
1844 Church of the Pilgrims established
1847 Plymouth Church established; Henry Ward Beecher installed as pastor
1849 Fire destroys Plymouth Church (January)
1850 New church completed (June)
1872 Henry Ward Beecher's Silver Anniversary at Plymouth Church (October)
1887 Death of Beecher; Beecher's funeral at Plymouth Church (March)
1888 Lyman Abbott installed as pastor
1898 Lyman Abbott's resignation announced (Fall)
1899 Newell Dwight Hillis installed as pastor
1902 Henry Ward Beecher Memorial plan instituted
1914 Arbuckle Institute dedicated
1918 Arbuckle Institute renamed Plymouth Institute (December)
1920 Plymouth Church damaged by fire (November)
1922 Death of Lyman Abbott (October 22)
1924 Newell Dwight Hillis disabled by cerebral hemorrhage; resignation announced
1927 James Stanley Durkee installed at Plymouth Church (January 27)
1927 Rose Ward Hunt returns to Plymouth Church on occasion of 80th anniversary of Beecher's first sermon at Plymouth Church (May 15)
1929 Death of Newell Dwight Hillis (February 25)
1934 Consolidation of Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims (Spring)
1939 Plymouth Institute renamed Plymouth Church House (May)
1940 J. Stanley Durkee's resignation announced (October)
1940 Plymouth Rock Celebration (December 21-23)
1942 L. Wendell Fifield installed at Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (May 22)
1951 Death of J. Stanley Durkee (September)
1954 L. Wendell Fifield's resignation announced (October)
1955 L. Wendell Fifield leaves Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (July)
1961 Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims designated Historic Landmark
1964 Death of L. Wendell Fifield (July)
Beecher Chronology
1813 Born, Litchfield, Connecticut; youngest child of Lyman and Roxana Beecher (June 24)
1830 Entered Amherst College
1834 Graduated Amherst College
1834 Began theological studies at Lane Seminary, Cincinnati, Ohio (July)
1837 Graduated Lane Seminary. Began first pastorate at First Presbyterian Church, Lawrenceberg, Indiana
1837 Married Eunice White Bullard of Massachusetts
1838 First daughter, Harriet Eliza, born (May 16)
1838 Ordained at First Presbyterian Church, Lawrenceberg, Indiana (November 9)
1839 Installed at Second Presbyterian Church, Indianapolis, Indiana (July 31)
1841 Son, Henry Barton Beecher, born
1847 Resigned from Indianapolis pastorate (August 15)
1847 Accepted call to Plymouth Church, Brooklyn (August 19)
1847 Installed at Plymouth Church (November 11)
1848 First mock enslaved persons auction at the Broadway Tabernacle, New York City (December 7)
1849 Plymouth Church destroyed by fire (January 13)
1850 Departed on first trip to Europe (July 9)
1850 New church completed according to Beecher's design (January)
1856 Sarah, an enslaved girl, sold for her freedom at Plymouth Church (June 1)
1856 Leave of absence taken from Plymouth to campaign for the election of John C. Fremont as President
1858 Great Revival at Plymouth Church
1859 Farm purchased in Peekskill, New York
1860 Enslaved girl Rose Ward Hunt auctioned for freedom (February)
1861 Appointed editor of the New York Independent (December 19; until 1864)
1863 Death of Lyman Beecher in Brooklyn (January 10)
1863 Departed on second trip to Europe; delivered speeches in England in support of the Northern cause (June)
1864 Campaigned for Abraham Lincoln
1865 Delivered address at raising of flag over Fort Sumter at close ofCivil War (April 14)
1865 Fall lecture tour on Reconstruction issues
1866 Published Cleveland Letters on Reconstruction (September)
1867 Novel Norwood published
1869 Elected president of the newly formed American Woman Suffrage Association
1870 Became editor of the Christian Union (October, until 1881)
1872 Week long ''Silver Wedding'' celebration at Plymouth for Beecher's twenty-fifth anniversary as pastor (October)
1875 Beecher-Tilton trial in Brooklyn (January-June)
1876 Summer/Fall Lecture tour
1877 Rutherford B. Hayes elected; Beecher's former defense lawyer,William Maxwell Evarts, appointed United States' Secretary of State
1878 Appointed Chaplain of 13th New York Regiment
1878 Completed construction of summer home, "Boscobel," Peekskill, N.Y.
1880 Cooper Institute speech for James A. Garfield and Chester A. Arthur presidential ticket (October)
1882 Resigned membership in New York Congregational MinisterialAssociation over position in support of the theory of evolution (October)
1883 Summer lecture tour on topic of evolution and religion
1883 Plymouth Church celebration of Beecher's 70th birthday (June)
1884 Speech in support of Grover Cleveland at the Brooklyn Rink (October 22)
1885 Delivered eulogy on death of Ulysses S. Grant (October 22)
1886 Sailed on the "Etruria" with Mrs. Beecher and agent, J.B. Pond, on last trip to Britain (June 19)
1886 Returned to New York (October 24)
1887 Preached last sermon, "I am Resolved What to Do" (February 27)
1887 Death of Henry Ward Beecher (March 8)
1887 Funeral Service at Plymouth Church (March 11)
1887 Buried at Green-Wood Cemetery (March 12)
Plymouth Church and Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims:
The Church of the Pilgrims, the first Congregational Church in Brooklyn, New York, was established in 1844 at Henry and Remsen Streets. Richard Salter Storrs was installed as its first pastor in 1846. As the population of Brooklyn grew and the number of congregants at Church of the Pilgrims increased, three of its members, John T. Howard, Seth B. Hunt, and Henry C. Bowen, with the assistance of David Hale from the Broadway Tabernacle Church, New York City, saw the occasion to establish a second Congregational Church in Brooklyn Heights. In 1847, nine additional members of the Church of the Pilgrims asked to be dismissed to help found this second church. By June of that year, a religious society with the name "Plymouth Church" had been formed. A certificate of incorporation was recorded in the clerk's office of Kings County on September 27, 1847.
Plymouth Church's first building had been that of Brooklyn's First Presbyterian Church. Plymouth Church purchased in 1846 this property, bordered by Orange, Cranberry, and Hicks Streets, when First Presbyterian relocated to Henry and Clark Streets. This property was initially purchased by John T. Howard, Seth B. Hunt, Henry C. Bowen and David Hale, and in June 1848 the property was transferred to the Trustees of Plymouth Church. The original Plymouth Church building was destroyed by fire in January 1849. The cornerstone for the structure of the new Plymouth Church was laid in May 1849, with the church opening its doors in January 1850.
The Reverend Henry Ward Beecher had been invited to speak at Plymouth Church prior to the church's incorporation. Members of the church, impressed with the young preacher, extended him a call to lead their congregation. Beecher accepted the call and was installed as the first pastor of Plymouth Church on November 11, 1847. Under Beecher's leadership, Plymouth Church expanded its role within the community; the church adopted missions, notably the Bethel Mission, at 15 Hicks Street, in 1866, and Navy Mission, located near the Brooklyn Navy Yard, in 1871. Both of these institutions existed prior to their formal association with Plymouth, but prospered under Plymouth's support and expanded the influence of the church to a more diverse population. The church and several of its affiliated organizations sponsored concerts, plays, and other social events that were not limited to members of the church. The anti-slavery position of the church was exemplified by its participation in enslaved persons auctions, which purchased the freedom of several enslaved persons. The church further expressed its anti-slavery militance by sending boxes of rifles marked "Bibles" to Kansas in 1854. These rifles, referred to as "Beecher's Bibles," were sent to support free soil settlers of Kansas, who were engaged in violent altercations with pro-slavery settlers regarding the status of slavery in the Nebraska and Kansas Territories.
Under the pastorates of Beecher and his successor Lyman Abbott, the number of congregants continued to increase with little change to the church's physical plant. During the pastorate of Newell Dwight Hillis (1899-1924), Plymouth Church underwent a great stage of physical growth that was seen most notably in the 1902 Henry Ward Beecher Memorial Plan. The major goals for this project included the installation of stained glass windows in the church that demonstrated the influence of Puritanism on the people of the United States and the nation itself, an endowment fund of $100,000, and the construction of a building to house an institute which would sponsor programs and activities organized by the church.
Additionally, this plan included developing property adjoining the church into a small park and arcade which connected the new building to Plymouth Church. The building was first named the Arbuckle Institute after Plymouth Church benefactor and member John Arbuckle, and was later renamed Plymouth Institute and then Plymouth Church House. The Institute provided many services and activities for the residents of Brooklyn Heights, such as classes in foreign languages and accounting, athletic activities, and social events.
As the population of Brooklyn Heights changed in the early 20th century, the number of members of both Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims declined. Many families of the middle and upper classes, which had previously been the main source of membership at both churches, left Brooklyn Heights. Their single family homes were divided into multiple units as Brooklyn Heights changed from a community of families and homeowners to a community of apartment dwellers, many of whom felt that the Congregational Church was not relevant to their lives. Both congregations were forced to reassess their positions within the community and their future economic stability.
In the spring of 1934, the congregations of Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims consolidated, creating Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims. The Reverend J. Stanley Durkee of Plymouth Church and the Reverend John Curry Walker of Church of the Pilgrims led the new congregation as co-pastors. Services alternated between the two churches at first, but following the resignation of Reverend Walker in 1935, an increasing number of church activities were held at Plymouth Church. It became further evident that Plymouth Church was to be the congregation's primary place of worship with the Plymouth Rock Celebration in 1940. During this event a piece of Plymouth Rock was transferred from the Church of the Pilgrims to the Plymouth Church House. By 1944, the Church of the Pilgrims building at Henry and Remsen Streets was purchased by a Maronite Roman Catholic congregation, becoming Our Lady of Lebanon Church. At that time, all activities officially moved to the Plymouth Church site at Orange and Hicks Streets.
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims was designated a National Historic Landmark in July 1961 by the United States Department of the Interior. Although the number of congregrants in the church does not compare to Beecher's time, the church continues to be an active member of the Brooklyn Heights community.
Henry Ward Beecher:
Henry Ward Beecher exercised his influence on many of the major social issues of the mid to late 19th century from his pulpit at Plymouth Church. Later eulogized as "the greatest preacher of his time," Beecher preached against slavery, for political candidates, women's rights, evolution, and his own idea of romantic Christianity that recognized "God's love for man and the availability of salvation for all." (Chadwick, 246; Clark, 4)
Beecher was born on June 24, 1813 in Litchfield, Connecticut, the youngest son of Lyman and Roxana Beecher. His father, a minister in the Presbyterian Church, was well known within the theological community for his advocacy of the "new religion," which endorsed personal salvation through conversion, an important emendation to traditional Calvinist theology. The younger Beecher studied at Amherst College, graduating in 1834, at which point he began his training at Lane Theological Seminary in Cincinnati, where his father had become president. Beecher married Eunice White Bullard, daughter of Dr. and Mrs. Artemas Bullard of Sutton, Massachusetts, upon his graduation from Lane in 1837. The young couple moved to Lawrenceberg, Indiana, soon after, where Beecher began his first pastorate at First Presbyterian Church. Beecher was called in 1839 to the larger Second Presbyterian Church in Indianapolis, where he began to make a name for himself as a gifted orator and preacher. The Beecher family left Indiana in 1847 when the newly formed Plymouth Church in Brooklyn called on Beecher to become its first pastor.
Beecher quickly imposed his energetic preaching style upon Plymouth Church and the congregation grew in number as the young minister became known for his dynamic and affective style, which appealed not just to local Brooklynites, but to ferry-loads of Manhattan residents and tourists from throughout the country. Beecher's articles and sermons were soon being published both nationally and internationally. He initiated the tactic of "auctioning" enslaved persons to purchase their freedom in 1848, a technique that won him both criticism and praise from the nation. His position as a member of a famous family of thinkers, including his father and sisters, writer Harriet Beecher Stowe and educator Catharine Beecher, increased his notoriety and popularity. Beecher's influence and wide interests led to his association and identification with major New York figures of the day, a group that included abolitionists, writers, and social theorists, as well as national and international personalities. Following a trip to England during the Civil War, where he spoke on behalf of the Northern cause, some contemporaries even began to credit Beecher with winning British support for the Union through his arguments and oratorical style.
For most of his life, Beecher involved himself in all levels of political campaigns as well as social issues. Using his pulpit as a platform, he supported candidates whom he felt could and would best promote social reform. He was a staunch supporter of Republican candidates John C. Fremont, Abraham Lincoln, James A. Garfield, and Rutherford B. Hayes, and was closely associated with that party. Still, Beecher felt confident enough to critique these major political figures and the party, supporting candidates whose policies best represented his own politics, as seen in his support of Democratic presidential candidate Grover Cleveland and his brief disassociation with, and criticism of, the Republican party in 1884.
Beecher devoted much of his time to literary pursuits as a regular contributor to a number of newspapers. He edited the New York Independent, a well known Congregational publication of the day, and later founded and edited the Christian Union (1870). His many lectures on life, art, literature, moral philosophy, and politics were gathered into volumes. He also authored a novel, Norwood (1867), a romantic depiction of New England life in the nineteenth century.
Beecher's wide scope of interests included history, art, the sciences, phrenology, and literature. He studied horticulture and agriculture. He had an affinity for architecture; he designed both the second Plymouth Church in 1849 and a summer home in Peekskill, N.Y. He was an extensive book collector and amassed a large private library over the years, the bulk of which was auctioned off at his death. These informal and formal pursuits informed his view of the world and the arguments that he espoused in his sermons and lectures.
Beecher's enthusiasms and his natural tendency to speak and act freely gained him many conservative critics, some of whom felt that he discredited his calling. His multiple enterprises, lecture schedule, and product endorsements afforded him a substantial income, which he used to purchase the material comforts he so enjoyed. Although this shared love of "the good life" endeared him to his middle-class congregants, his religious peers often took issue with this lifestyle, which was far from that of the traditional "modest preacher." He also earned criticism for what Clifford Clark reported in 1978 as his "romantic Christianity... a religion of the heart, an appeal to the feelings and emotions that replace[d] the cold, formalistic evangelical theology of the previous generation and [which] accepted the new theories of evolution and biblical criticism." (Clark, 3)
After the Civil War, Beecher's name became even more famous and controversial because of accusations of adultery. In October of 1872, sex reform advocate Victoria Woodhull accused Beecher of committing adultery with Elizabeth Tilton, the wife of Beecher's onetime protege, Theodore Tilton. The charge took root, and Tilton, then editor of the Independent, took his former friend to court. The six-month long trial was a worldwide news event, but culminated in the acquittal of Beecher in June of 1875.
Beecher overcame the scandal and his popularity appeared to grow in its aftermath. In 1876, he embarked on a lecture tour, traveling throughout the United States. In 1880, he endorsed the Republican presidential ticket of James A. Garfield and Chester A. Arthur in a speech at the Cooper Institute in New York City. He resigned his membership in the New York Congregational Ministerial Association in 1882 due to his belief in evolution, around which he centered an 1883 lecture tour. Still, his congregation continued to follow their beloved pastor and in 1883 the church celebrated his seventieth birthday.
Throughout the rest of his life, Beecher continued his travels and his lecture tours, continuing to support causes and political candidates. He delivered a famous eulogy for Ulysses S. Grant in 1885 and, only a year prior to his death, made a last trip to Britain. Henry Ward Beecher died on March 8, 1887, at the age of seventy-three. His funeral became an outpouring of loyalty and affection. Memorials and testimonies were published throughout the world and the anniversary of his death was remembered for years to come. Organizations were formed in his name, and no less than twenty biographies have since been written about his life, including one by Social Gospel advocate Lyman Abbott, Beecher's immediate successor at Plymouth Church.
Lyman Abbott: